<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon occasioned by the death of the Right Honourable the Lady Guilford by Philip Horneck ...</title>
            <author>Horneck, Philip, 1673 or 4-1728.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 40 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 18 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A44544</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing H2854</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R8311</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13530814</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13530814</idno>
            <idno type="VID">99988</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A44544)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 99988)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 790:32)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon occasioned by the death of the Right Honourable the Lady Guilford by Philip Horneck ...</title>
                  <author>Horneck, Philip, 1673 or 4-1728.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 31, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Edmund Rumball ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata: p. [8]</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Duke University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Guilford, Elizabeth Greville North, --  Baroness, 1669-1699.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Proverbs XXXI, 31 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-02</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-03</date>
            <label>Scott Lepisto</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:99988:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:99988:1"/>
            <p>A SERMON Occaſioned by the DEATH OF THE Right Honourable, THE Lady <hi>G<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ILFORD.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By <hi>Philip Horneck,</hi> L. L. B. Chaplain to the Right Honourable, <hi>Francis,</hi> Lord <hi>Guilford.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>Edmund Rumball,</hi> at the <hi>Poſt Houſe in Ruſſel-ſtreet,</hi> in <hi>Covent-Garden.</hi> MDCXCIX.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:99988:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:99988:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <head>The Epiſtle Dedicatory, TO THE Right Honourable, FRANCIS, Lord <hi>G<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ILFORD.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>MY LORD,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>WHilst others Mourn in Silence the Loſs of the Deceaſed Saint, I must beg leave to make a Publick Declaration of my Grief, tho it must fall ſhort of a true <hi>Sympathy</hi> with Your <hi>Lorſhip</hi>'s; who, being Related to her in the ſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctest Alliance, best knew the value of her while Living, must ſenſibly perceive the want of her now Dead.</p>
            <p>This, <hi>my Lord,</hi> would Naturally draw on a Conſolatory Diſcourſe, were I not fully aſſur'd of the Preſumption of ſuch an Attempt. Your <hi>Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> is furniſh'd with better Arguments than I can give; the happy effects of which, appear in that true ſettlement and compoſure of your Spirits.
<pb facs="tcp:99988:3"/>I that ſaw Your <hi>Lorſhip</hi>'s demeanour at the moſt Melancholy Juncture, with what <hi>Chriſtian</hi> Cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and Conſtancy you receiv'd the News of My <hi>Lady</hi>'s Death, how Glorious you roſe above the Billows which threaten'd you, cannot doubt but the ſame Principles which fortify'd you at that time, have ſince confirm'd you beyond a poſſibility of falling. Such exemplary Conduct, <hi>My Lord,</hi> was highly requiſite to ſecure the Interest of <hi>Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion;</hi> for had Your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> fail'd in that great Point of <hi>Reſignation,</hi> Hundreds that ſtood beneath your Shade, might have ſtagger'd in their Belief, when they had ſeen ſo Tall a Cedar ſhatter'd and broke by the aſſaults of Fate. But ſtill Your <hi>Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi>'s Grief was comely, your Lamentations well-temper'd: All the Tenderneſs and Paſſion that could be fairly allow'd, Your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> expreſs'd; yet, at the loweſt ebb, never betray'd a <hi>Sorrow with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Hope.</hi> This was truly Great, and Rational; for, as a <hi>Philoſopher</hi> of old obſerves, <hi>It is not Benevolence, but Weakneſs, that prompts a Man to continual Grief, and makes thoſe only fear whom Reaſon has not ſufficiently arm'd a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt Contingencies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And here I cannot but Congratulate Your <hi>Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip</hi> upon bearing the Stroke ſo well: For none can
<pb facs="tcp:99988:3"/>imagine how near a touch Nature gives, how pier<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing the Sufferings of one's Blood are, but thoſe whoſe tender Bowels feel the Smart; and I dare affirm no Perſon, of ſuch quick Reſentments as Your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> is Maſter of, could have ſet bounds to their Paſſion: None beſides your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> but muſt have fainted under the Load. In fine, No Perſon that had once enjoy'd ſo voluable a Conſort, but would have courted Solitude for ever. But Your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> has bravely Surmounted the buſy En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>croacments of Nature, and wiſely conſidered that this Ineſtimable Prize was ſnatch'd from as by the ſpecial deſignation of <hi>Providence. Vertue</hi> has no ſecurity from the <hi>Grave; Death</hi> riots on the ſpoil of the beſt as well as the worſt, <hi>Cato</hi> enquires of the Gods <hi>why Pompey ſhould be vanquished by Caeſar, who had much the bet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter cauſe.</hi> We may likewiſe wonder, but with more Modeſty, <hi>Why the Rightous Perish, and the wicked Survive and Proſper.</hi> No doubt the Almighty has great reaſon for ſuch ſevere diſpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſations, either that we are not worthy of them, or that me prize them too much: In this late ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rowful Inſtance, I hope, I ſhall not exceed the bounds of Modeſty, if I aſcribe the <hi>former</hi> to <hi>our ſelves,</hi> the <hi>latter</hi> to Your <hi>Lordship;</hi> For Your <hi>Lordship</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:99988:4"/>muſt own, you Lov'd her, Lov'd her dearly; nay, Lov'd her paſſionately. This God ſaw, and, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps, deprived Your <hi>Lordship</hi> of ſo great a Bleſſing on purpoſe to draw of your Thoughts from all <hi>Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lunary</hi> things. This is the reſult of his boundleſs Knowledge, who foreſees what is beſt for us, and mingles ill with the good things of this Life, Fears with our Hopes, Croſſes with our greateſt Pleaſures, leaſt we ſhould ſet too great a value upon any thing here below, and abandon <hi>Heaven</hi> for <hi>preſent Frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> The Spirit is apt to yield in Proſperity, and we grow too frequently upon the liberal Diſtributions of <hi>Providence,</hi> till God humbles us by Affliction, recalls our wandring. Thoughts, and out of theſe Clouds creates a Glorious Day. As to theſe follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>Pages,</hi> I have little to offer in their behalf, and therefore muſt beg Your <hi>Lordship</hi>'s Protection, both for them and my ſelf. The firſt <hi>Eſſays,</hi> in any kind, are hazardous, but Attempts of this Nature are al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt deſperate. For upon ſuch occaſions we are un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>avoidably expoſed to one of theſe two Cenſures, either of ſaying too little, or too much: The latter of which Imputations does no ways concern me; For how pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>valent ſoever the Malice of the World may be, I will venture to affirm, that I have not, neither was I in a poſſibility of doing Juſtice to <hi>My Lady;</hi> For thoſe
<pb facs="tcp:99988:4"/>
               <hi>Characters</hi> I have drawn are only <hi>Sketches</hi> of her Life; but could I have been led into her Retirements, I do not queſtion but there might have been form'd one of the compleateſt Models that has been exhibited to the World for ſome Ages paſt. Indeed, thoſe ſcat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter'd Pieces of her Life, ought to have been toucht by a more maſterly Hand, but I had no power to diſpute Your <hi>Lordship</hi>'s Command, which will, in ſome mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, I hope, attone or the Defects. Here I muſt not forget to acquaint the World what repeated Hints. I receiv'd from Your <hi>Lordship</hi> to avoid all artificial Strains, falſe Colourings, and ſuſpicious Gloſſes. Theſe I have ſtrictly obey'd; nay, I have went ſo far as to lay aſido even common Ornaments that I might not endanger the truth of the <hi>Character.</hi> And now, <hi>My Lord,</hi> it's time to ask Pardon for this trouble, but, at the ſame time, muſt beg Your <hi>Lord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ship</hi> to indulge one <hi>Plea</hi> (if it may be admitted as ſuch) That the miſcarriages of Young Adventurers are more excuſable than others; eſpecially where neither Raſhneſs or Ambition has any hand in the Attempt. From theſe Crimes I can ſafely abſolve my ſelf; and if Your <hi>Lordship</hi> will be pleas'd to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give the reſt, it will be a mighty Encouragement to the green Enterprizes of,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>MY LORD, Your Lordſhip's moſt Devoted Servant and Chaplain,</hi> PHILIP HORNECK.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:99988:5"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>Page 30. line 25. read her for our</p>
         </div>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:99988:5"/>
            <head>A Funeral-Sermon ON Proverbs XXXI. xxxi.</head>
            <head type="sub">And let her own Works praiſe her in the Gates.</head>
            <p>THIS Chapter contains the True and Genuine Character of a Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous Woman, with relation to a Married State. The proper Offices and Employments are ſpecify'd, and her Vertue is plac'd not only in Prayer, and Devotions, but likewiſe in the prudent Conduct of her Domeſtick Affairs; Inſtruction of her Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren,
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:99988:6"/>and keeping much at home. Theſe Qualifications the Wiſe Man exacts of the Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>male Sex, and prefers them to Beauty, Shape, or any other outward Accompliſhments. <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour is deceitful, and Beauty is vain, but the Woman that feareth the Lord, ſhe ſhall be praiſed.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And leſt any one ſhould Object, that it's poſſible, after having done ſo many laudable Actions, no perſon will ſet a due value on them, he prevents all fears of this nature, by adding, that her own works will praiſe her: <hi>And let her own works praiſe her in the Gates.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The ſole difficulty contain'd in the Words, depends upon that Phraſe of being <hi>praiſed in the Gates.</hi> For the clearing of which, be pleas'd to obſerve, that in ancient times the publick Seats of Judicature were fix'd in the Gates of the City; to the end that all Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſengers might ſee Juſtice impartially diſtributed; and if any Perſon, either going or coming, had any juſt Plea againſt the Sentence pronounc'd, he might offer it in favour of the Party Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demned. Theſe Gates being publick Places where all Cauſes were try'd, and the common
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:99988:6"/>Tranſactions of the World brought in; the meaning of the Expreſſion comes to this iſſue; even <hi>That a Perſon ſo Meritorious, as is repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſented in the preceding Lines, ſhall have the honour of receiving publick Praiſe and Commen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation.</hi> Her Praiſes ſhall not be confin'd to the ſingle breath of her Neighbours, but proclaim'd with a general voice; her Merits ſhall not lie conceal'd within the walls of her own Houſe, but flie abroad, and become the ſole Diſcourſe of the Town.</p>
            <p>Here might be ſome uſeful Doctrines rais'd from the Text, but I fear they would be too General; beſides; the Solemnity of this Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion Commands me to particularize; and the Il<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luſtrious Vertues of the Deceas'd, to whoſe Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mory we Sacrifice, Challenges from me more than the compaſs of theſe following Pages will admit of. A Perſon whoſe eminent vertues raiſed her beyond equality, and have now given her a propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionate Glory amongſt the Saints above. A Perſon whoſe Death calls for general Mourning, but a tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcendant ſorrow from the <hi>good;</hi> a Perſon of whom the World was not worthy; In fine, a Perſon of whom ſhould I ſpeak but modeſtly, the time would fail me. The Theme is ſpacious and might well ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:99988:7"/>enlargements; but I ſhall endeavour to keep within the bounds of your patience and atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. Truth ſhall be my Guide through the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral Scenes of her Character; and indeed ſhe wants no adventitious Gloſſes to ſmooth over the Hiſtory of her Life. That Tongue is to be ſuſpected which is purely tun'd to the Ear; and Falſhood, we know, delights in borrow'd Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naments, whilſt Truth appears more comely, and Triumphs in her Primitive Nakedneſs, and Simplicity. The Object will appear truly Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious, without the advantage of falſe Mirrours, ſo that I am under no temptation of mixing the Colours to advantage, or making the Touches appear more lively, for <hi>her own Works ſhall praiſe her in the Gates.</hi> Yet this muſt not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude our pious Officiouſneſs, or debar us the pleaſure of recounting her Vertues; it's fit they ſhould be convey'd down to Poſterity, that fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Ages may <hi>admire,</hi> and commemorated at this time, that the preſent Age may <hi>imitate</hi> them. It is not ſufficient to ſay that a Perſon was good, without amplifying upon the Character; Particulars always leave the deepeſt impreſſion, and excite the Generous to emulation. But here I am at a loſs where to begin, freſh Beau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:99988:7"/>crowd in and dazle us, Wonders lie diſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed thro' the whole Series of her Life, and each Minute conſiſted of Actions Great and Memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable.</p>
            <p>The Infancy of moſt Perſons is deſervedly paſs'd over, containing little elſe but Simplici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, and innocent Paſtime; and Relators are cautious of introducing them upon the Stage, leſt they ſhould ſully the Actions of their ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per years. But here even theſe tender Minutes muſt not be loſt; for whilſt others of her Age purſued their Childiſh Diverſions, ſhe was at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentive to good Advice; whilſt others trifled away their time, ſhe would be asking Queſtions ſurprizing, and much above her Age.</p>
            <p>She was early poſſeſs'd with an awful Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of God, and with the conſequence of that, an eſteem for Religion. It's true ſhe had been excellently well Principled, as being un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the Care and Direction of Worthy <note n="*" place="margin">The Right Honourable <hi>Foulk</hi> Lord <hi>Brook,</hi> and his Pious Lady.</note> Parents; and with <hi>Timothy, from a Child had been in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed in the Holy Scriptures.</hi> But ſtill there was ſomething too remarkable in her at thoſe years, to eſcape our acknowledgment, <hi>viz. her Religious Doubts;</hi> for ſhe would be ſcrupulous even about indifferent Matters, and could not
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:99988:8"/>be prevail'd with to enter upon an Action which ſeem'd doubtful. This was not the ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect of Superſtitious Fears; her Soul was ever exalted above any encroachments of that Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture. The truth is, ſhe had form'd to her ſelf a due Notion of God's infinite Goodneſs, and from thence made this natural Inference, <hi>That he was of purer eyes than to behold the leaſt ſhadow of Iniquity,</hi> which made her ſo ſtrict and cautious.</p>
            <p>When very young, ſhe expreſs'd a ſtrong deſire to go to the <hi>Holy Sacrament,</hi> and would frequently entertain her ſelf with the thoughts of that Bliſs ſhe ſhould reap from thence. She ſoon became ſenſible of what ſhe had promis'd in her <hi>Baptiſmal, Covenant,</hi> and was eager to confirm and ratifie thoſe Engagements at the Altar. But ſtill ſhe ſuſpected there was too much raſhneſs in her Deſire, and forbore till ſhe came to maturer years. Theſe Holy Fears were ſure Prophecies of her future ſtrictneſs, and her Dawn being ſo Glorious, no wonder that the Day proved ſo bright.</p>
            <p>As ſhe grew up, the impulſe was ſo ſtrong upon her, that it could be no ways reſiſted; and accordingly ſhe appear'd at the <hi>Holy-Table.</hi>
               <pb n="7" facs="tcp:99988:8"/>But what Conflicts did ſhe ſuffer? What dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferent Paſſions ſtrugled in her Breaſt? Fear left ſhe ſhould prove an Unworthy Receiver; Joy that ſhe was admitted to ſo great an Honour, as to be made a Partaker of the Benefits accruing from the Death of her Saviour. Her Tranſports after Receiving were too great to be conceal'd; ſhe profeſs'd there was no pleaſure on this ſide Heaven comparable to it, and that it was the richeſt and moſt ſatisfactory Banquet ſhe had ever taſted. The Joy ſhe found, was a mighty encouragement for her to perſiſt in that Duty, and her preparations to it were ſtrict and Labo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious. All her thoughts came under Correction; and as ſhe kept Minutes of her Life, ſo nothing of the leaſt importance could eſcape her Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge. She was always free from Reſerves, but before a Communion ſhe would lay open her Soul, make the ſtricteſt Animadverſions, and heighten each Treſpaſs into a Crime; and even after the ſevereſt Scrutiny, would be ſelf-diffident, and lay the beſt of her Services at the foot of the <hi>Croſs.</hi> She look'd upon it as an high Indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity to turn her back upon the <hi>Holy Table;</hi> and where ever ſhe found a remiſneſs in the Celebra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of that Ordinance, ſhe heartily bewail'd the
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:99988:9"/>Neglect, and was forward in promoting ſo im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portant a Duty.</p>
            <p>From her Infancy ſhe was an early Riſer; and what the Ancient <hi>Philoſophers</hi> enjoyn'd as neceſſary to the preſervation of Health, ſhe pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed upon a Religious account. No ſooner waking, but impatient till ſhe was upon her Knees. She always began the Day with Praiſes to God for the paſt Nights preſervation, and then haſted to her Cloſet to beg his protection of her the following Day, in a more humble and ſolemn manner.</p>
            <p>This Retirement generally laſted from Six to Eight in the Morning; part of which time was ſpent in Reading the <hi>New-Teſtament,</hi> with An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>notations upon it; and wherever ſhe lighted on a paſſage applicable to her ſelf, or fell in with relations of Great and Exemplary Men, ſhe would pitch on them for Subjects of her enſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Meditation.</p>
            <p>She conſtantly Pray'd five times a Day, and how ſhe demean'd her ſelf in the Cloſet, may be eaſily gathered from the order and regularity of her publick Devotions. There was nothing light orſuperficial appear'd thro' the whole Series of the Action; ſhe perfectly Wreſtled with God
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:99988:9"/>for a Bleſſing, and the Sacrifice was purified with Fire. So obſervant ſhe was of the moſt decent Poſtures in Prayer, that when there was an abſolute neceſſity for her being excuſed Kneel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, it was with great difficulty ſhe was brought to comply. If once upon her Knees, no buſineſs of the greateſt importance could raiſe her before the Service was ended.</p>
            <p>Indeed ſhe was ſo entirely fix'd upon the Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty in hand, as not to be aware of common Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturbances. No ſudden Viſits, or fear of break<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing an Appointment could tempt her to a Neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect; and if any Perſon of the higheſt Rank came in at the beginning of the Service, ſhe would in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite them to joyn with her, and Congratulate them upon coming in ſo ſeaſonable a minute. Her Zeal in this Caſe did not burn inwardly, but diffuſed it ſelf thro' the whole Family, whoſe attendance ſhe conſtantly required; and no ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſe could attone for their abſence, after ſhe had given Orders that all Buſineſs ſhould be poſtpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to the Service of God, or totally omitted, rather than any failure ſhould occur in thoſe Holy Exerciſes.</p>
            <p>And here the Tranſition to her Faſting is very natural. She conſtantly Faſted once a Week, but
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:99988:10"/>would not tie her ſelf up to a ſet Day, on purpoſe to avoid diſcovery. When prevented by Company, or any extraordinary Occaſions, from Faſting on the Day ſhe propos'd, the Concern was ſo great as to draw Tears from her eyes; and if any Bu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſineſs interven'd on that day ſhe actually Faſted, ſhe thought the Mortification lame and imper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fect.</p>
            <p>Her Abſtinence in the time of <hi>Lent</hi> is almoſt incredible, arriving very near to that which the Primitive Fathers call <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> the <hi>Faſts of Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perpoſition,</hi> the moſt exquiſite ſort obſerved by the ancient <hi>Monks.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This was ſo far from creating impatience in her, that her Spirits were more compoſed in the Evening, and a double ſprightlineſs and vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vacity played in her Countenance, ariſing from Peace within, which was a continual Feaſt to her. Such a tender frame as hers, would have adminiſtred fear to others, and put them upon great caution in the Treatment of it; may they would have concluded ſuch Severities impracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cable, and ſat down with the diſcharge of milder Duties; but ſhe was unwilling to impoſe upon her ſelf, and plead inability before an attempt.</p>
            <pb n="11" facs="tcp:99988:10"/>
            <p>She was reſolv'd to try the utmoſt of her ſtrength, believing that uncommon Supports were vouchſaf'd to thoſe who ran the Race with Cheerfulneſs; of which ſhe taſted in an eminent manner, inaſmuch as ſhe was enabled to go through thoſe Severities without any viſible decay in her Health.</p>
            <p>The Recreations ſhe took lay out of the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon Road; for ſhe could by no means allow of thoſe which generally paſs under that plauſible Name. There was too much Impertinence, in her Opinion, allied to the common Viſits of the Age, to be very fond of them. Beſides, the many idle words, and detracting Stories which paſs interchangeably at ſuch times, diſcouraged her from being frequently engaged in them. Plays were Diverſions ſhe never admired; and if ſhe chanced to go, it was owing more to the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunity of her Friends, than her own In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clinations.</p>
            <p>And to be plain, her complacency to the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral humour of the Age, in this particular, was purely that Religion might not ſuffer any imputati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as if it render'd its Votaries peeviſh and ill-humour'd. Whenever ſhe went, ſhe always inform'd her ſelf firſt of the Character of the Play, never
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:99988:11"/>venturing to go, except repreſented to her as inoffenſive to Good Manners; for a profane Expreſſion made her turn pale, and jeſting with Serious Matters chilled her Blood.</p>
            <p>Of late the Stage has been ſo Corrupted, the Characters ſo Obſcene; in ſhort, the whole Plot and Artifice of the Play ſo Deſtructive to the Great Ends of <hi>Religion,</hi> that ſhe grew more and more averſe to them. In all other Recreations ſhe was ſo far from Tranſgreſſing, that ſhe al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways kept within the Bounds of <hi>Chriſtian Liberty.</hi> Her ſprightlieſt Hours had their Allay, for ſhe qualified her Joy with Fear and Trembling; and her Diverſions, to ſay the Truth, were Great, and Inſtructive.</p>
            <p>For want of Employment, Perſons of her Lofty Station are apt to run into exceſs of Va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity; and not knowing how to ſpend their time, lie open to a thouſand Temptations. Thus whilſt they think themſelves Privileged by their Quality to ſit Idle, they inſenſibly fall from do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Nothing, to that which is worſe than No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing.</p>
            <p>Againſt this Danger ſhe was fully ſecur'd, by being always well employ'd; <hi>Eſſays, History, Morality,</hi> with the like, took up all the vacancies
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:99988:11"/>ſhe could ſpare from the ſtricter Duties of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</hi> She had too fine a Taſt to reliſh any thing mean or trifling. The Hiſtories of our Nation ſhe had made her own; and that Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, which would have ſatisfy'd a common Curioſity, did but inflame her deſire of knowing more; for ſhe pierced beyond her Native Clime, enquired into the riſe and fall of remote <hi>Empires,</hi> the variety of Laws and Eſtabliſhments, with the like. Theſe were the Subjects of her En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tertainment. And there was nothing extant in our own Language, too great for her <hi>Genius</hi> to compaſs; for ſhe had a wonderful quickneſs of apprehenſion, with that peculiar Bleſſing of a correct Judgment. Being always thus happily employed, little time remain'd for the lower ſort of Diverſions; neither was it poſſible for one of ſuch exalted Principles to deſcend from thoſe heights ſhe poſſeſs'd; for ſuch ſtudies as theſe fix the Mind upon what is laudable and ſerious, and prevent waſting the time in Luxury and Fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. And <hi>that Woman</hi> (as <hi>Plutarch</hi> obſerves in his Conjugal Precepts) <hi>who is ſtudious of Geome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try, will never affect the wanton motions of a Dance. And ſhe that is charmed with the ſublime notions of</hi> Plato and Zenophon, <hi>will look with
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:99988:12"/>diſdain upon laſcivous Novel and amorous Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mance.</hi> Her collection of Books was very choice, and none could find admittance there but thoſe which carry'd Uſe as well as Entertainment a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>long with them.</p>
            <p>This Converſation with the Dead, was as pleaſant to her as with the Living, and ſhe heartily pity'd thoſe who complain'd of Solitude, and want of company, when they had ſuch va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riety in their Cloſets; often repeating that old Axiom, <hi>That ſhe never found more company than when ſhe was alone.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>She was free from Paſſion of any kind, and could command her ſelf upon the greateſt occaſions, without the trouble of running over the <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phabet.</hi> Indeed ſhe was of ſo fine a Complex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ion, that no particular quality or humour had the Aſcendent over her; and upon that account was not ſo apt to be raiſed on a ſudden; and before it came to any dangerous height, ſhe had time to prepare her ſelf againſt it. There was ſuch a due balance in her Temper that it kept her from unuſual Tranſports on one hand, and mean Depreſſions on the other. The only thing that was able to create a changein her, was, <hi>The loſs of a dear Friend or Relation:</hi> At ſuch
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:99988:12"/>a Juncture, the tenderneſs and flexibility of her Soul was diſplayed; But theſe were Reſent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments which proceeded from a Principle of Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, and were out of hers, as well as others power to prevent. And indeed the contrary, which is the <hi>Stoical Apathy,</hi> or rather Brutiſh Inſenſibility, extinguiſhes all that ſociable Love which is ſo very neceſſary to the Creature, and the very Cement of human Society. Still, at the Criſis of ſuch a Tryal which was as pain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful to her as a ſever'd Limb, She never parted with her Reaſon, but always conquered the Paſſion before it became <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nchriſtian.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Gracious and pleaſant, like a Morning Sun, ſhe broke forth upon all, as well Strangers as Familiars. There was a ſettled chearfulneſs dwelt on her Brow, which beſpoke her always conten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted, ſuch happy Lines as expreſſed the Sinceri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of her Soul. To this was joyn'd a wond<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Humility, eaſineſs of acceſs, and condeſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion both to the Ignorance and Weakneſs of others, tho' ſhe knew at the ſame time what was due to her Station, as well as any of her Rank; but ſhe could not endure a ſervile diſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance, conſidering all Chriſtians as fellow Members of the ſame Body.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:99988:13"/>
            <p>Theſe mighty Gifts and Accompliſhments ſoon made her Conſpicuous, and drew not only the Eyes, but the Hearts and Affections of all People unto her: Still amidſt theſe Applauſes ſhe maintain'd her Ground; ſhe induſtriouſly ſhunn'd Popularity, and affected to live in Shades: But Alas! that was a vain Attempt; for the Beams of her Goodneſs ſoon pierc'd the Cloud which had conceal'd it, and diſcover'd her in the moſt private Receſſes. There are few Perſons but what are ambitious of telling the World what they know; and this Vanity is more excuſable in the Female Sex, when they arrive to ſuch diſtinguiſhing Heights: But certainly no Perſon that ever knew, or did ſo much, cared to inform the World leſs of it. <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> was wont to ſay, <hi>That the ſweetest Muſick was a Man's own Praiſe.</hi> She was juſt of the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Opinion; and nothing was more untuneable, than to hear People run out into <hi>Eulogies</hi> and Commendations of her. She thought Praiſe too nearly related to Flattery and Lies: and as ſhe never admired herſelf, ſo ſhe could not bear to be commended by another.</p>
            <p>She often expreſſed a great Contempt of the World, and thought no Time ſo ill ſpent as
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:99988:13"/>that which was laid out in Dreſſing. Trains and Attendance were always uneaſie to her: She accounted Greatneſs no better than Gilded Slavery, and many Servants but a civiler Sort of Guard. The Plaineſt Dreſs pleaſed her moſt, and if ever She put on any thing more Airy and Ornamental than uſual, it was to avoid Singularity, and to comply with thoſe Perſons whoſe Commands She never diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted.</p>
            <p>She was very nice in the choice of her Friends; civil to all, only the Good were dear to her; and thoſe that had the Honour of being eſteemed ſo, might conclude themſelves happy; for (not to mention her readineſs to aſſiſt them in their greateſt Exigencies) in the ſtricteſt Friendſhip She would never omit reproving an Indecency; for She thought mutual inſpection and advice to be the proper Branches of it, and was as faithful to her Friends as their own Conſciences. As She never was prepoſſeſs'd againſt any one upon a doubtful repreſentation, ſo She would not contract an intimacy upon the ſcore of 2 or 3 plauſible Actions, but would firſt obſerve the variety of their Sentiments, Turns and Affections, at different Junctures;
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:99988:14"/>and if they anſwered her expectation, they were Enrolled amongſt the happy number of her Favourites. This made her Friendſhip more Valuable and Laſting: And, after ſhe was once fix'd, it was no eaſy matter to diſplace her Eſteem.</p>
            <p>Her Charity had no Bounds; all Taſted of her Benevolence; and I dare affirm ſhe never diſmiſs'd a true Object unrelieved. But ſhe would not ſtay for their coming to ask a Boon: Her care and vigilance Anticipated their Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>queſts, and the frequent Supplies ſhe convey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by different Hands are ſtanding Monuments of her Bounty in that kind.</p>
            <p>She was a ſtrict obſerver of the Sabbath, and never miſs'd the Publick Service of the Church, unleſs prevented by Sickneſs; and even at that time the uneaſineſs upon her Spirits, for ſtaying away, was ſo great, that without a Gracious Providence, might have increaſed the <hi>Malady.</hi> Her attention at Church, was always fix'd; and having the advantage of a Tenacious Memory, ſhe could eaſily Command, not only the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Heads, but likewiſe all the material Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſages in a <hi>Sermon,</hi> which ſhe committed to Short-Hand before Dinner, and afterwards digeſted
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:99988:14"/>more Regularly, in order to ruminate on them the ſucceeding Week.</p>
            <p>Her Inclinations were very much bent to a ſingle Life; fearing that the Incumbrances atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dant on a Married State would engroſs too much of her time. But all theſe Jealouſies vaniſh'd when ſhe found ſo Pious and Chearful a concurrence in her <hi>Noble Lord</hi> for promoting thoſe good Deſigns ſhe had form'd to her ſelf beforehand. And here I muſt not omit one thing which I have in Command to make Publick, <hi>viz.</hi> that <hi>My Lord</hi> found her Example and Perſwaſion of that infinite uſe and advantage to him in the Affairs of Religion, as to own her the happy Inſtrument, next under God, of reviving thoſe good Habits which were near Dying in him thro' neglect of Improvement. This no ways depreciates the Character of that Great Man. This is no more than what Men of Rank and Eminence have confeſs'd before. <hi>Valerianus</hi> ow'd his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſion to his Wife <hi>Cecilia, Sizinius</hi> to <hi>Theodora,</hi> and <hi>Adrianus</hi> was tempted to Dye a Martyer thro' the Inſtigation of his Wife <hi>Natolia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Further, all that had the Honour of knowing the Deceaſed <hi>Saint,</hi> muſt confeſs her Power was Irreſiſtible: And no wonder ſhe had ſuch an
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:99988:15"/>Influence over <hi>Him</hi> in a concern of this Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, where beſides the Commanding Excellency of Religion, Love on his ſide prepared the way, and Innumerable Charms on her's where alway ready to Second the Requeſt.</p>
            <p>To amplify at laſt upon her Duty, Love, and Honour; To tell you ſhe was ſingularly Prudent in the management of her Domeſtick Affairs, That ſhe was a Woman of the trueſt Conduct, and Studious of the Credit of her <hi>Lord,</hi> were but to leſſen the Dignity of the former Characters; for no one will ſuppoſe that a Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon who made ſo great a proficiency in the Sublimeſt parts of <hi>Religion,</hi> could poſſibly fail in the Subordinate Points.</p>
            <p>Yet there is one thing more that deſerves our Remembrance, <hi>viz.</hi> Her Meditations upon moſt of the <hi>Evangelical</hi> Duties, which I have had the Honour of peruſing ſince her Death. They are all Lofty and Divine. The ſtrains of them are raiſed ſo far above the Common level of Mortality, that they appear to me no leſs than the <hi>Raptures of expiring Saints.</hi> Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they are all of her own compoſure, I am not able to determime: But ſure I am there is an
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:99988:15"/>acceſſion of her Thoughts by the Style and Tenour of the writing.</p>
            <p>In the <hi>Zenith</hi> of her Health, She would frequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be talking of her Diſſolution, and ſpeak of Death as of a Familiar Friend; and I know no Parallel ſo exact as that of the Famous <hi>Marcella, St. Jerome</hi>'s Friend, of whom the Pious Father re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports, <hi>That ſhe conſtantly led ſuch a kind of Dying Life, that ſhe fancy'd her ſelf Old and Decaying before ſhe Remembred that ſhe was Young and Handſom; and every time ſhe diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>robed her ſelf, ſtill the thoughts of ſhifting her Earthly Tabernacle Sprung up in her Mind.</hi> Thus the Bleſt Soul ſpent her Days. And now the Tragick part comes on. Here I could willing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly be excuſed, and with <hi>Timanthes</hi> the <hi>Painter</hi> throw a Veil over the reſt. But there were too many Obſervables in the laſt Minutes of her Life to lye concealed. Here Illneſs was ſudden and ſurprizing, and the fierceneſs with which it aſſailed her at firſt, ſeem'd to carry Mortality along with it. However ſhe had nothing to do but to Dye; and had the firſt ſtroke proved Fatal, ſhe could have departed with Old <hi>Simeons</hi> Faith and Aſſurance. But God was pleaſed to reſpite her for ſome time. After ſhe came out of her Fits, which continued for two Days, with
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:99988:16"/>little Intermiſſion: She expreſſed no Impatience tho' her Tortures were exceſſive. No ſooner had ſhe gathered up a few Remains of ſtrength, which were all too little to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bat with the Diſtemper, but ſhe employ'd part of them in Praiſes to God for the ſeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Deliverance. The Night before her de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parture ſhe renew'd her Petitions with ſuch Vehemence, that nothing but immediate relief could have ſecured her from fainting away. After this the favourable Symptoms vaniſhed, and we could no longer flatter our ſelves when the decay was ſo viſible; yet ſhe retained a Quick and Active ſenſe, and as her Spirits flagg'd and deny'd her utterance, her Holy Breathings increaſed. A peculiar Sweetneſs lodged on her Countenance in the Bittereſt of her Pangs, and her Face ſeem'd to be im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pregnated with Heavenly Light. Being made ſenſible of Approaching Death ſhe diſcovered no change, but talk'd free and unconcerned about her Funeral. No Diſcompoſure appear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in her but what the Tears and Groans of the ſorrowful Attendants created; and that proceeded from a Tenderneſs of Soul in her, for ſhe was intirley reſigned and more pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:99988:16"/>to depart than we were to loſe her. As our Sorrows increaſed ſhe endeavoured to. moderate them, and comforted us with the poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſibility of her Living, tho' ſhe knew it was her Gain to Dye: And indeed ſhe was the fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſt Perſon to give Advice, even in thoſe languiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing minutes, as being more ſettled and compoſed than any about her. Her Soul was ſerene to the laſt; and no wonder, ſince ſhe had this Teſtimony from her Conſcience, That <hi>in God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Simplicity and Sincerity ſhe had converſed in the World.</hi> She called for the Bleſſed <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crament</hi> ſome Hours before her Departure. That was always her proper Cordial; but at this juncture it revived her beyond the Richeſt Drops; for her Strength and Activity after receiving was Remarkably Superior to what ſhe had poſſeſs'd ſome hours before, and had her Spirits continued Freſh and Vigorous to the end, had her Power been equal to her Deſire, How <hi>Seraphick</hi> would the laſt Act of her Life have been? What lively Deſcriptions would ſhe have given us of the <hi>New Jeruſalem?</hi> In what Heavenly Raptures would ſhe have given up the <hi>Ghoſt?</hi> But God in his infinite Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom thought fit to deny us that Bliſs, whilſt
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:99988:17"/>ſhe, happy Soul! poſſeſs'd it all within. A ſilent Joy had filled all the Channels of her Soul, and like a Deep Stream ran gently thro' her. A Joy ſhe had which was better felt than Expreſt. A Joy ariſing from a full Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidence in God. A Joy Immenſe and Raviſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing; and in the middle of the <hi>Comendatory Prayer</hi> reſign'd her Innocent Breath into the Hands of a Faithful Creator. Thus the bright Star Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pired: Thus the Glory of the Age, the beſt of Women, Dyed, and her Longing Soul ſoon took its way to the Manſions above. Thus fell the Beautious Pile, and the ſine Lineaments of her Face ſoon loſt their ſplendour. Thus the Temple was deſtroyed, and the Fair gueſt ſoon quited its abode. Yet ſtill the good Works ſhe hath done are left behind her: They will <hi>Praiſe her in the Gates</hi> and give her Immortality. They will Survive the ſhort date of Inſcriptions, and proclaim her worth beyond the reach of Talkative Tomb<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtones. This can only qualify the mighty loſs, whilſt the contemplation of her Divine Excellencies muſt give us a lively Image of what ſhe was, and preſent her as Living, to our view. It was not barely the deſcent from
<gap reason="missing" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page missing〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:99988:17"/>lluſtrious Houſe that could have enbalm'd her Name: Honour of it's ſelf is but a ſhort liv'd Meteor, which no ſooner appears but Dyes, unleſs ſupported by virtuous Actions, but here was Greatneſs and Goodneſs in conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, which will make her Shine with a double Luſtre. It's an eaſy matter to convey a Name down to Poſterity; the worſt as well as the beſt Actions have been commemo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rated; but to be talked of with pleaſure and to be Numbred amongſt the Juſt in future Ages, is the only thing that can make us covet to be Remembred. This muſt not tempt us to affect Vain-glory, or do good Works for Oſtentation ſake. In a true Piety, tho' many commendable Actions may lye concealed, yet enough will be diſcovered to ſatisfy the World that we are really better than we appear to be; and few emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nently good have Dy'd unregarded, tho' it has been their Fate to live in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moteſt Corners. To inſtance no further than in this Pious Soul now reſting with God, none could be more ſilent in their Devotions; Indeed her greateſt Actions lay moſt retired from common inſpection, yet
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:99988:18"/>all her Induſtry could not prevent their being known.</p>
            <p>What remains now but to propoſe this great Example to your imitation? And there needs not many Motives when the Intrin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick Charms are ſo inviting. Would you be admired by the Pious in your Life-time, or bewail'd in the Grave? This your good Works muſt procure you. Are you fond of an honourable Name after your Deceaſe? This your good Works muſt Eſtabliſh. In fine, Would you appear truly Glorious to Poſterity? Your Goodneſs muſt create the Rays. And are not thoſe great Inducements to be vertuous? Are all our good deſires extinct? Is all our Zeal decayed? Will none of theſe Arguments work us up to a reſemblance of theſe Graces, or raiſe in us a Spirit of Emulation? <hi>Themiſtocles</hi> we hear complaining, that the <hi>Trophies</hi> of <hi>Miltiades</hi> will not let him Sleep; And ſhall not the much greater Achivements of this Female worthy, Rouze us from our Slumber? Let us no longer trifle away our Time, but fothwith ſet about the good Work, and Tread in our Steps. This will furniſh us with a Joy ineffable
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:99988:18"/>when we come to lye upon our Death-Beds. This will create Peace within; ſuch a Peace which the World cannot give. The Thoughts of having done well will make our Death eaſy, and our Paſſage ſure to thoſe Eter<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>l Seats above. Our good Works will make us ſmell ſweet in the Grave, ſweet as Flowers with the Morning Dew upon them; ſuch pleaſant Odours has the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> Saint left behind, whoſe loſs we deplore; ſuch as will ever Flouriſh and Maintain their Fragrancy. Hiſtories ſhall perpetuate her Name ſo long as the <hi>Sun</hi> and <hi>Moon</hi> endures; and at the Reſurrection of the Juſt her good Works ſhall be proclaim'd in the Gates of the <hi>New-Jeruſalem.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
